<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pillar and pattern of Englands deliverances. Presented in a sermon to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen, with the several companies of the City of London, in their solemn meeting at Pauls on the Lords Day, Novem. 5. 1654. Being also the first Sabbath after his Lordships entrance upon his majoralty. / By Thomas Horton Doctor in Divinity, and professor thereof in Gresham-Colledge London.</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E815_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 124:E815[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pillar and pattern of Englands deliverances. Presented in a sermon to the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen, with the several companies of the City of London, in their solemn meeting at Pauls on the Lords Day, Novem. 5. 1654. Being also the first Sabbath after his Lordships entrance upon his majoralty. / By Thomas Horton Doctor in Divinity, and professor thereof in Gresham-Colledge London.</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R.I. for Jo. Clark, and are to be sold at the entrance into Mercers Chappel, at the lower end of Cheap-side.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 5 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1654.</note>
                  <note>The Thomason copy is bound with items from November of 1654.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XXIII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114972:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PILLAR and PATTERN OF Englands Deliverances.</p>
            <p>Preſented In a Sermon to the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, with the ſeveral Companies of the City of <hi>London,</hi> in their ſolemn Meeting at <hi>Pauls</hi> on the Lords Day, <hi>Novem.</hi> 5. 1654.</p>
            <p>Being alſo the Firſt Sabbath after his Lordſhips entrance upon his Majoralty.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS HORTON Doctor in Divinity, and Profeſſor thereof in <hi>Greſham-Colledge LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 77.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will remember the Works of the Lord; ſurely I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy WONDERS of old.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 COR. 1.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who delivered us from ſo great a Death, and doth deliver, in whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Jo. Clark,</hi> and are to be ſold at the entrance into Mercers Chappel, at the lower end of Cheap-ſide. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114972:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO The Right Honourable</hi> Chriſtopher Pack <hi>Lord Mayor, with the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court of Aldermen of the famous City of</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Devil hath had a double Deſign about this buſineſs of the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon;</hi> the Firſt was to blow up the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Second is to blow up the <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and to make it appear leſs to the World than indeed it is. It is true, I will not deny, but that as Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will be ſure to be at the end of every Action, ſo there might be poſsibly ſome <hi>Politique</hi> advantages made of the Diſcovery of this Plot, by ſome which had then the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of preſent Affairs; but that is no <hi>Diſparagement</hi> at all to the <hi>Mercy</hi> it ſelf, nor <hi>excuſe</hi> to thoſe which were <hi>Inſtruments</hi> in the Conſpiracy. The <hi>Danger</hi> was unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, and the <hi>Preſervation</hi> very remarkable, and ſuch as we have <hi>All</hi> cauſe very deeply to lay to heart, with the fulleſt reſentment that may be. The ſcope of this plain <hi>Sermon</hi> is a little to help us herein, which I have now at the laſt by <hi>your</hi> Order (not of <hi>mine own</hi> inclination, nay indeed with ſome <hi>reluctancies</hi> in my ſelf) brought to the publique <hi>Light,</hi> but in a deſire of the publique <hi>Good.</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:114972:3"/>have purpoſedly deferred it to this <hi>Time</hi> for the publiſhing of it, that ſo, as the thing it ſelf was as the beginning of a <hi>New Life,</hi> ſo the Diſcourſe about it might fall in with the <hi>New Year,</hi> wherein our Lives are in a manner reſtored and renewed unto us. Beſides that, the time of <hi>Printing</hi> it might ſomewhat anſwer the time of <hi>Preaching</hi> it, which was <hi>New-Year</hi> in the Calendar of the <hi>City,</hi> as it is now in the Calendar of the <hi>World.</hi> And laſtly, That as the <hi>Deliverance</hi> is a Monument of Gods goodneſs to the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo the <hi>Sermon</hi> might be a Teſtimony of mine own reſpects and thankfulneſs to <hi>your ſelves</hi> in the injoyment, and likewiſe continuance of ſo much favour and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from you, as I am ſtill partaker of. I have this only to adde, That the <hi>Lord</hi> who keepeth <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and who alone is the ſafety of his people, would delight ſtill to watch over this <hi>City</hi> for good, to make the <hi>Walls</hi> of it <hi>Salvation,</hi> and the <hi>Gates</hi> of it <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Officers</hi> of it <hi>Peace;</hi> to eſtabliſh <hi>Holineſs and Righteouſneſs</hi> within the borders, and in the midſt of it, that it may prove an <hi>eternal excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency,</hi> and the <hi>joy of many Generations,</hi> which is and ſhall be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Greſham-Colledge <date>January <hi>1. 1655/4.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Servant in the work of the Lord:</hi>THO. HORTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114972:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached in PAULS on the Fift of <hi>November,</hi> being alſo the <hi>Lords day, A. D.</hi> MDCLIV.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NUM. 23. ver. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Surely there is no inchantment againſt Jacob, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any divination againſt Iſrael. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this time it ſhall be ſaid of Jacob, and of Iſrael, WHAT HATH GOD WROVGHT!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day on,
<note place="margin">The Occaſion.</note> which wee are now met, and aſſembled together at this time, <hi>(Right Honourable and Beloved in our Lord)</hi> it carries the ſignature of a <hi>double</hi> Solemnity upon it; the one in its <hi>weekly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, as it is the <hi>Lords</hi> Day, the Day which God hath ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more eſpecially for his own ſervice; And the other
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114972:4"/>in its <hi>annual</hi> revolution, as it is <hi>our</hi> day, the Day which God hath marked with an eminent, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous deliverance of this Land and Nation, of which wee are, from that horrid and dreadfull conſpiracy of the <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon.</hi> In either of which reſpects, it is a time much to be obſerved, and regarded by us <hi>throughout our Generations;</hi> and in reference whereunto wee may ſay of it, in the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, this is the Day which the Lord hath made,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 118.24.</note> wee will be glad and rejoyce in it.</hi> Hee hath made it to be a Day of <hi>Reſt,</hi> and he hath made it to be a day of <hi>Joy</hi> both. And theſe two, they do no way croſs, or contradict one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but do very happily agree together: for wee can never better ſanctily a Sabbath, than by works of <hi>Prayſe,</hi> nor wee can never better celebrate a Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, than by works of <hi>Piety.</hi> Indeed, <hi>every</hi> thankſgiving-Day is in the proper nature of it <hi>a Sabbath,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly (if wee rightly underſtand it) is in <hi>that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to be kept by us, as an <hi>Holy</hi>-day, not as a <hi>play</hi>-day; as a day of <hi>holy and ſpiritual merriment</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing to the Lord; but this which is now before us, is ſo (as I may ſay in a manner, whether we will or no, from the preſent frame, and diſpoſition of the year, which therefore I hope wee ſhall improve to the beſt advantage of the duty it ſelf; that is, not to prophane the Sabbath, that we may keep the Feſtival, but rather by keeping of the Feſtival, ſo much the better to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>I may adde one Notion to it more (though inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to the other two, yet not altogether to be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by us) which makes it more ſolemn yet. It is the day wherein the <hi>chief Magiſtrate</hi> of this City appears firſt in this place, with that badge of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114972:4"/>upon him, who cannot lay a better begining and foundation of ſuch an imployment, than this of Praiſe and Thankſgiving to God; eſpecially (as the occaſion now calls to) for protection and preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from danger, being that, which thoſe that are Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, as they have moſt need <hi>of,</hi> ſo they have moſt promiſe <hi>for,</hi> of any men elſe beſides. All theſe, they concurr and meet together in this preſent perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</p>
            <p>But that which I ſhall eſpecially frame my diſcourſe unto is the commemoration of the <hi>deliverance it ſelf,</hi> which I have anſwerably fitted with a Scripture, as I conceive moſt ſuitable to it, in the prophecy of <hi>Balaam</hi> upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The occaſion briefly was,
<note place="margin">The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> this <hi>Balak</hi> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> hearing of the general ſucceſs which the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> found, in all places whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they came, and withall underſtanding of their pitching in the plains of <hi>Moab,</hi> beganne hereupon to be diſtreſt and fore afraid. And now, partly to ſecure himſelf, and partly to diſpleaſure the Iſraelites, ſends to <hi>Balaam</hi> the Magician to curſe them. The Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſeemed at firſt to be unwilling, but being incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by <hi>Balaks</hi> promiſes of reward, attempts it, and that often, though in vain. Inſtead of <hi>curſing</hi> hee <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> them; yea with his own mouth ſignifies, that no curſing could prevail againſt them; <hi>Surely there is no inchantment, &amp;c.</hi> And thus are wee now come to the Text, Wherein wee have two general parts obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>deliverance</hi> or preſervation it ſelf.
<note place="margin">The Diviſion.</note> And</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>celebration</hi> of the deliverance. The deliverance it ſelf, that is layd down by way of <hi>ſolomn declarations</hi> in the firſt branch of the verſe, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114972:5"/>is no inchantment &amp;c.</hi> The Celebration of the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<note place="margin">The Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance under a threefold Conſideration.</note> that is by way of <hi>prophetical prediction</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. According to this time it ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. wee beginne with the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Deliverance or Preſervation it ſelf, <hi>Surely there is no &amp;c.</hi> Now this again may bee looked upon three manner of waies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In its propoſition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In its reduplication.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In its Reflexion.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition of it that is <hi>abſolute; no inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Jacob.</hi> The Reduplication of it, that is the ſame Truth in a <hi>diverſity</hi> and variety of expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>no inchantment againſt Jacob,</hi> no divination <hi>againſt Iſrael.</hi> The Reflexion of it, that's this Truth conſidered as comming out of the mouth of ſuch a perſon as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered it, wicked <hi>Balaam,</hi> a ſorcerer, one who was of the Counſel of <hi>Balak</hi> an enemy to God and his people.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 In it. Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> to look upon it in the bare ſimple and abſolute propoſition, <hi>There is no inchantment, or divination, againſt Jacob, or Iſrael.</hi> Interpreters doe ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer concerning the reading of theſe words; for ſome read them thus, There is no Inchantment <hi>in Jacob,</hi> nor no divination <hi>in Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Thus the <hi>Septuagint, Saint Hierom,</hi> and the <hi>Vulgar Latine,</hi> yea our own laſt Tranſlation in the <hi>Margin,</hi> as ſome others afore it <hi>in the Text,</hi> making it a part of the praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the People of God, that they had no ſuch Arts as thoſe of Sorcery &amp; Witchcraft amongſt them.
<note place="margin">1 In <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </note> And ſo the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe hath it expreſly, <hi>Inchantments are not pleaſing in the Houſe of Jacob, neither doth the multitude of the Houſe of Iſrael delight in divinations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In particular no Sorcery.</note> This, it hath a very good ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with it, and ſuch as may bee profitabely impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114972:5"/>for our inſtruction; to ſignifie how ill ſuch Studies and wayes, as thoſe of Aſtrology and Magick, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination, doe become thoſe which profeſſe Religion; being ſuch things, as the Church of God in all times of the World hath profeſt it ſelf an Enemy to them, and God himſelf hath taken them off from them, as we may ſee in divers places of Scripture tending to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but I will not trouble you with them now; I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give you an hint of it by the way, as lying before us.
<note place="margin">In General, no indirect means.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wee may carry it (if wee pleaſe) a little further, by taking <hi>Inchantments</hi> and <hi>divinations here</hi> by a <hi>Synecdoche Speciei,</hi> for all ſinfull and unlawfull <hi>means, as</hi> to the compaſſing of any deſigne. There is none <hi>of theſe</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Gods people; <hi>Gracious</hi> and holy perſons, ſo far forth as they have Grace in them, and where they are not ſurprized by a Temptation, they do abhor &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelves from all unjuſt and unwarrantable Courſes for the effecting of any buſineſſe whatſoever. And this now <hi>Balaam</hi> might ſeem to ſpeak (though as wee ſhall hear afterward, by a Spirit above his own) in oppoſition to what was practiſed by <hi>himſelf,</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak</hi> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> in attempt againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi> They made uſe of ſuch meanes as <hi>theſe</hi> were (as we may ſee in the ſtory); but as for <hi>Iſrael themſelves,</hi> which were Gods people, they did not do ſo. The Servants of God living by faith in his promiſes, doe content themſelves in the uſe of thoſe means which himſelf hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not diverting or ſteping aſide to any thing which is unconſcionable, though it were to gain the whole World it ſelf. Thus, if we will, wee may expound one verſe by another; that in this verſe, by that in verſe 21. <hi>In this</hi> verſe, There is no inchantment <hi>in Jacob, nor any Divination in Iſrael. In that, Hee hath not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114972:6"/>Iniquity in Jacob, neither hath hee ſeen perverſneſse in Iſrael.</hi> That is, Iniquity and perverſneſſe <hi>of this kind,</hi> whereof hee now ſpeaks, and which by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies was uſed againſt them, God ſaw none of <hi>this</hi> now in his people; though for <hi>other</hi> matters hee ſaw enough, yea and ſaw it likewiſe <hi>with effect,</hi> ſo as to correct and chaſtiſe them for it. But ſo much of <hi>that</hi> Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by reading the word <hi>In: In Jacob</hi> and <hi>in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Interpretation is that before us, <hi>No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment againſt Jacob &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Againſt <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi>
               </note> And ſo the Prepoſition in the Hebrew is oftentimes uſed. This is not to be underſtood in regard <hi>of indeavour,</hi> but <hi>of ſucceſſe.</hi> If wee ſpeak of indeavour, ſo there are inchantments enow againſt the people of God, there is no want of attempts upon them; nor will not be, whiles there is a Devill in the World to joyn with corrupt Nature, but as to the <hi>ſucceſse,</hi> here they fayl. Many <hi>a time have they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted mee from my youth, may Iſrael ſay; Many a time have they afflicted mee, but they have not prevailed againſt mee. Attempting</hi> is one thing, but <hi>Prevailing</hi> is an other; And this the Enemies of the Church want. No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment ſhall <hi>hinder Jacob,</hi> or prejudice him; ſo the <hi>Arabick,</hi> which is the proper ſenſe of the Text. For the better opening and amplifying of this preſent paſſage to us, wee may look upon <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a threefold notion or acception, in which they may be taken,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> in a threefold acception.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Perſonal; Secondly, National; and Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Myſticall, or Repreſentative.</p>
            <p>According to the Firſt; ſo it point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out a particular Perſon, as the Patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> was; whoſe name <hi>was called upon the Family,</hi> or by whoſe name the Family was called. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 48.16. According to the Second,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114972:6"/>ſo it relates to that particular Nation and State, and Common-wealth of the Jews. According to the Third,
<note place="margin">1 Myſtical, or, repreſentative.</note> ſo it ſignifies the whole Church and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Beleevers, ſtyled by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, the Iſrael of God. Gal.</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p>We will begin with the laſt firſt, as that which is moſt conſiderable, as it referrs to the whole Church, And ſo wee have this in it,</p>
            <p>That all Plots and Conſpiracies, and Indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours againſt the Church of God, they are in vain, and to no purpoſe. They are ſuch as are as good as none, being none in the <hi>event.</hi> This is clear, from the Text; <hi>Balak</hi> would have <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſtroyed. How does he go about to effect it? Hee calls <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe them, a man of his own diſpoſition, forward enough to ſuch a work, but being further incouraged with hopes and expectations of preferment, very eager and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt upon it; and yet for all that, it would not do, his inchantments and ſorceries would not take, but like ſo many ſparks of fire falling into the main Ocean go out of themſelves. And ſo it is with all others, which are imployed in the ſame work, they meet with the ſame ſucceſſe ſooner or later.
<note place="margin">Pro. 11.18.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) work a deceitfull work;</hi> and they never work it more truly than in their indeavours againſt the Church: Here it is a deceit full work indeed, and ſo will prove, in regard of the miſcarriages and diſapointment which it is ſubject unto. And that twofold, Firſt,
<note place="margin">Enemies miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariage double.</note> Sometimes in the thing it ſelf, which they labor to effect. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, At leaſt, and always, as to the evill and miſcheivouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt as to the thing it ſelf,
<note place="margin">1 Of Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</note> they fail now and then here. So it was in this preſent inſtance of <hi>Balaams</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114972:7"/>of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Hee could not proceed ſo much as to the performance; though hee indeavoured it, and went about it, yet hee ſtill miſcarried in it, and could not do it at all. According to that of <hi>Eliphaz Job</hi> 5.12. <hi>hee diſappointeth the decrees of the crafty, ſo that their hands cannot perform their enterpriſe.</hi> God ſometimes will not ſuffer the enemies to effect that particular plot, which they deſign and propound to themſelves.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, If they chance to do that, yet they reach not what they intend in it. God may ſuffer a plot to take, as to the <hi>performance,</hi> and yet to fail, as to the principall end; becauſe it does not work the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the parties, which it is laid againſt. As we ſee in the great contriver and complotter of al, Satan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who miſcaries even then, at ſuch a time as hee ſeems to ſucceed; in as much as whiles hee does ſome things which are <hi>materially</hi> prejudicall to the Church, yet God keeps them from that abſolute ruine which hee intends to them in it.</p>
            <p>And yet thats not all which is conſiderable in this point neither, there is ſomewhat more, as pertinent to this purpoſe, and that is this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That theſe indeavours prove at laſt to the Churches advantage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the greater diſadvantage of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt. To the advantage of the Church. Theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments and Divinations are ſo farre from being <hi>againſt Iſrael,</hi> as that they make rather for it; Thus it was here in this buſineſſe of <hi>Balaam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Of Diſ-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</note> as to the curſing of Gods people; Inſtead of curſing them, hee bleſſes them; he does not only <hi>not do</hi> that which <hi>Balak</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to do, but hee does that which is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114972:7"/>to it; ſo farre from ſubjecting them to miſcheif, as that hee ſo much the rather confirms good upon them, yea and that <hi>Balak</hi> himſelf could ſee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs too at length. Therefore, he who was ſo fierce at firſt to perſwade <hi>Balaam</hi> to <hi>curſe</hi> them, is fain at laſt to call upon him to <hi>ſuſpend,</hi> and to do nothing with them at all, ver. 25. of this Chapter, <hi>And</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Balaam, <hi>neither curſe them at all nor bleſs them at all;</hi> Do not <hi>bleſs</hi> them, leſt they prove to be happy; do not <hi>curſe</hi> them, leſt even that curſe it ſelf turn to a greater Bleſſing to them. God will make the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys of his Church, before he has done with them, <hi>weary</hi> of plotting miſchief againſt them, by converting that miſchief of theirs, which is plotted by them, to his peoples greater good.</p>
            <p>Yet this is not all yet, there is ſomething further in it ſtill; God does not onely convert theſe Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies to the greater advantage of the Church, but moreover to the confuſion of the <hi>Enemy;</hi> ſo that now there is no inchantment againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> but rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Balak,</hi> nor any Divination againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but rather againſt <hi>Balaam</hi> himſelf; againſt <hi>Moab,</hi> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Church.</hi> They that wiſh ill to <hi>Sion,</hi> and curſe <hi>that,</hi> their curſes and ill wiſhes ſhall fall upon their own heads, and turn to the ruin of thoſe from whom they proceed. We need not go far for inſtances of this kind, we have enow of them continually before us, and ſtanding upon record, in <hi>Pharaoh, Herod, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel, Julian,</hi> and the reſt of that wicked crew; ſo ſure and certain is this obſervation here preſented unto us. That no indeavors againſt the Church ſhall be ſucceſsful, no weapon that is formed againſt <hi>them ſhall proſper,</hi> and <hi>every tongue that riſes in judgement againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114972:8"/>them ſhall be condemned, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 54.17.</p>
            <p>Would we know whence this comes about;
<note place="margin">The Grounds.</note> It is eaſie to give an account of it.
<note place="margin">1 Gods Affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion.</note> Firſt, From the intereſt which they have in <hi>Gods Affection;</hi> They are the Dear ones and Beloved of the Lord. Love it is a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Affection, which is anxious and ſolicitous for the party which it is faſtened upon, that no evil may at any time betide it; and thus it is with God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Church; It is much in his <hi>heart,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is much in his <hi>preſervation:</hi> He <hi>loves it,</hi> and therefore <hi>defends it,</hi> and keeps it from wrong, according to that famous place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.3. ſpeaking concerning the Church, <hi>Sing ye unto her a Vineyard of red wine. I the Lord do keep it, I will water it every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, leſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day.</hi> There is no man can be more chary of a Vineyard, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, or Garden of his own plantation, and which his own hands have ſet, than the Lord is of his Church and People, which his own hands have made and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned, which are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. Theſe are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and tender in his eyes; and he hath a ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto them, for the preſerving and ſecuring of them. His bowels here yern in him, as Queen <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> ſometime did in her, upon the like occaſion, <hi>How can I indure to ſee the evill that ſhall come unto my people? or how can I indure to ſee the deſtruction of my kindred?</hi> Heſt. 8.6.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 His Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> The Church are a people <hi>in Covenant,</hi> therefore a people preſerved: They have given up themſelves to him, and therefore may very well expect to be ſecured by him. Protection is a part of Gods bargain with his people, when he takes them to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114972:8"/>his, and they him to be theirs. <hi>Fear not, Oh</hi> Jacob, <hi>I am with thee, be not diſmaid, I am thy God, Iſa.</hi> 41.10. God having once taken us to be his own, ingages him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to keep us from all kind of evill whatſoever, ſo far forth as it is fitting for us; <hi>The Lord will preſerve me from every evil work,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we <hi>take it actively or paſsively,</hi> from <hi>doing</hi> evill, or <hi>ſuffering</hi> it, from both he will preſerve me, from his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ingagement to me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 His Intereſt.</note> Gods <hi>own honor</hi> is concerned in the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Church, who are a people addicted to him, and keep up his name in the world. The conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies which are laid at any time againſt the Church of God, are not ſo much againſt <hi>the Perſons</hi> as <hi>the Cauſe;</hi> not ſo much againſt theſe or thoſe <hi>men,</hi> as againſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> which is profeſſed by them, and <hi>the Worſhip,</hi> which they give themſelves to, from whence, God himſelf is intereſted in the protection of them. So bleſſed and happy a thing is it to be found in good ways, and to be maintaining of good cauſes, that whiles we ſtir for the promoting of <hi>them,</hi> we defend <hi>our ſelves,</hi> becauſe we make God a party with us, ſo that he cannot <hi>forſake us,</hi> but he muſt <hi>deny himſelf.</hi> Therefore there is no <hi>Inchantment againſt Jacob,</hi> becauſe there is no <hi>Device againſt God. There is no wiſdom, nor counſel, nor underſtanding againſt the LORD, Prov.</hi> 21.30. They that plot againſt the Church, they plot againſt God himſelf, his Cauſe, and Truth, and Worſhip, and all that is his, and how can they think to proſper, or ſucceed in it?</p>
            <p>But ſo much of the firſt Acception of the words, <hi>Jacob and Iſrael,</hi> taken <hi>myſtically,</hi> or repreſentatively, for the <hi>whole Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114972:9"/>
            <p>The ſecond is,
<note place="margin">2 National.</note> as taken <hi>Nationally,</hi> as pointing out that particular Church, and State, and People of the Jews; for ſo the words do commonly import in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and there is a Truth in the Propoſition ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, That all endeavors, as againſt the whole Church in general, ſo againſt any Church, or State, or Nation whatſoever in particular, which God does own, and take into his protection, they are in vain alſo. It was the privilege of theſe people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they were the <hi>Darlings,</hi> and beloved of God; The Lord choſe them from all other Nations, and People beſide in the World, to be a peculiar people to himſelf, and his own inheritance: Now theſe, notwithſtanding, does <hi>Moab</hi> here let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt, but vainly, and with no ſucceſs at all; Thoſe whom God will bleſs, they ſhall be bleſſed, maugre all oppoſition to the contrary. <hi>How ſhall I curſe, whom God hath not curſt? or how ſhall I defie, whom the Lord hath not deſied?</hi> ſays <hi>Balaam</hi> himſelf to this purpoſe, verſ. 8. of this Chapter. <hi>Happy is the people that is in ſuch a caſe; yea, bleſſed is the people, whoſe God is the Lord,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.13. And again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the</hi> NATION <hi>whoſe God is the Lord, and the people whom he hath choſen for his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance;</hi> They are bleſt, and bleſt by God, and whiles they <hi>are ſo,</hi> no curſings of men ſhall reach them, or prevail againſt them. That is the ſecond ſenſe of the words, as taken <hi>Nationally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is,
<note place="margin">3. Perſonal.</note> as taken <hi>Perſonally. Jacob and Iſrael,</hi> they are the Proper Names of <hi>one man,</hi> and they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Truth in them ſo; teaching us thus much from them, That God does not onely take care of the whole Church in general, to preſerve that, but alſo of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114972:9"/>every private Soul and Member of it in particular; God takes care not onely of Nations, but of perſons; not of <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely, but of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Take notice of that. And this he does, whether as to keep them from the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf, or of his <hi>Inſtruments;</hi> For Satan himſelf, Chriſt has vanquiſhed him, and beaten him already, not onely for himſelf, in his perſonal conflict with him, but alſo for all his members, which are related to him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32. And ſo for <hi>his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they</hi> ſhall not prevail neither againſt thoſe which are good in their particular perſons: Let it be as to <hi>Sorcery,</hi> and <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> and <hi>Inchantment,</hi> taken in the letter; there is for this a great ſecurity upon them; or as to any thing elſe beſides, they are in that alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Providence. The times of the Servants of God are in his hand, and their lives are at his diſpoſing, ſo that none can take them away, but as he pleaſes. <hi>Act.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Fear not</hi> Paul, <hi>for I am with thee, and none ſhall ſet upon thee to hurt thee, for I have much people in this City.</hi> God preſerves all his Servants, but eſpecially any, as they are of more publick and greater imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Magiſtrates and Miniſters, and the like. He hath a double fence for them, to guard them and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them from evill, and the aſſaults of evill men, from evill hands, from evill tongues, and from evill devices, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19, 20. Thus much of the words alſo <hi>perſonally;</hi> And ſo much likewiſe of them in the ſimple and abſolute propoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is in the <hi>Reduplication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">II. In the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duplication.</note> Not onely <hi>no inchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, but beſides, <hi>No divination againſt Iſrael;</hi> the ſame Truth repeated in a diverſity and variety of expreſſion; and that for this reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, to ſhew the certainty of the thing it ſelf, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114972:10"/>in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dream, which was doubled, becauſe the thing was eſtabliſhed; Even ſo it was here; It was a reſolved and determined caſe, and that alſo upon the experiences even of <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi> themſelves; they had endeavored it again and again, as to the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it; to curſe them here, and to curſe them there, to double curſes upon them; and here now according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they have a double acquittance from it in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemination of the phraſe, that ſo there might be no queſtion made of it, but be received for an undoubted Truth, it is therefore double.</p>
            <p>Now therefore are we anſwerably to entertain it,
<note place="margin">The Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and to be perſwaded of it, and to it, improve it to the beſt advantage that may be.
<note place="margin">1 For Comfort</note> It is a point of ſingular comfort and incouragement to the people of God, that the caſe is thus with them; that whiles they <hi>dwell in the ſecret place of the moſt High, they abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty, Pſal.</hi> 91.1. That they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and protected by God himſelf, from the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and Attempts of Enemies plotting againſt them, who though they may uſe their endeavors, yet ſhall not prevail; or if at one time, yet not at another. They may prevail a little for a while, to encourage them, and harden them ſo much the more in an evil courſe, and to further their deſtruction; but they ſhall not prevail at laſt, ſo as to get the better of the Church; This ſhall not be granted unto them. They may prevail over a <hi>party,</hi> but they ſhall not prevail over the whole <hi>Generation</hi> and company of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: They may prevail over the <hi>Preacher,</hi> but they ſhall not prevail over the <hi>Truth;</hi> over <hi>the Perſon,</hi> but not over <hi>the Cauſe;</hi> over the <hi>life,</hi> but not over the <hi>heart,</hi> and ſpirit, <hi>this</hi> they ſhall not do.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114972:10"/>
            <p>Which further, in the next place,
<note place="margin">2 For Terror.</note> ſerves for a word of amazement, to all ſuch perſons as thoſe are which ſet themſelves againſt them; that they do herein but loſe their labor, yea, which is worſe, conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves. Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37, 12, 13. <hi>The wicked plotteth againſt the juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth, but the Lord ſhall laugh at him, for he ſeeth that his day is a coming, He that fitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. Men</hi> may laugh ſometimes at that which they do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and which they cannot hinder, or prevent; but when <hi>God</hi> laughs, there's ſomewhat more in it than ſo; <hi>He</hi> laughs at the plots of wicked men, as diſcerning the vanity of them, and as being able to fruſtrate and defeat them: And whiles <hi>He</hi> laughs <hi>in ſcorn,</hi> they have no cauſe to laugh <hi>in triumph. His laughter</hi> it may juſtly provoke <hi>their tears,</hi> as being a fore-runner of ruin unto them; <hi>He will laugh at their deſtruction, and mock when their fear commeth, Prov.</hi> 1.26. Yea, as he will laugh <hi>himſelf,</hi> ſo he will cauſe the <hi>Church</hi> to laugh with him, as ſhe did againſt <hi>Aſhur, Iſa.</hi> 37.22. <hi>The Virgin the Daughter of</hi> Syon <hi>hath deſpiſed thee, and laughed thee to ſcorn, the Daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>hath ſhaken her head at thee.</hi> God vouchſafes to his Church and people an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly triumph over their Enemies, whiles they think to inſult over them, As <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9, 10. <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves, O yee people, and yee ſhall be broken in pieces; and give ear all yee of far Countries; gird your ſelves, and ye ſhall be broken in peeces, gird your ſelves, and ye ſhall be broken in peeces. Take counſel together, and it ſhal come to nought; ſpeak the word, and it ſhall not ſtand, for God is with us.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> If God be with us</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>who can be againſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that is, ſtill as I ſaid before, ſo as to hurt us. If we ſpeak
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114972:11"/>as to matter of <hi>Diſ-affection,</hi> ſo there are <hi>enow</hi> againſt us, and more than could be wiſht. Men do no ſooner look after God, or God after them, but they have <hi>Multitudes</hi> of people againſt them; but againſt them, ſo as to <hi>conquer</hi> them, that they are not, nor cannot be.</p>
            <p>How much does this then ſurther inlarge the <hi>Honor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> For Exulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> as well as the <hi>Safety</hi> of the Church of God, and ſerve to draw others into it! who would not now be in the number of Gods ſervants, and in love with the ſtate of Gods people, who have ſo great a privilege as this belonging unto them! <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael, who is like unto thee O people, ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thine excellency!</hi> It is the <hi>Epiphonema</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> unto them in his bleſſings of them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. And may be applied to the whole Church, in all times and ages of the world. And thus much of this Truth here delivered, both in the <hi>Propoſition</hi> and <hi>Reduplication</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The Third and laſt is in the <hi>Reflexion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">III The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection.</note> as comming from <hi>Balaam.</hi> Speeches they have regard given unto them, much according to the quality of the perſons from whom they proceed. And ſo it is with this here before us: It was a Truth in it ſelf, but it was more wonderfull from the party that uttered it. If either <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Joſhua</hi> had ſaid as much, wee ſhould not have thought it any Great matter. But for <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> to ſay it, was incredible. What! <hi>Balaam!</hi> A <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer!</hi> an <hi>Idolater!</hi> an <hi>Enemie</hi> to God and his people! for <hi>him</hi> to let fall ſuch a ſpeech as this is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Balaam</hi> under a double notion.</note> it was beyond all expectation. There is a twofold Notion under which wee may look upon him.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 A wicked man.</note> As a <hi>wicked</hi> man, and yet ſpeaking that which was <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114972:11"/>
            <p>Secondly, as an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and yet ſpeaking that which was <hi>comfortable,</hi> and to the incouragement of Gods people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A wicked Man, and yet ſpeaking that which was good. VVee ſee here, how good ſpeeches may ſometimes come from bad men. Thoſe which are themſelves naught, and rotten, and unſavory, yet they may now and then utter, &amp; let ſlip from them, that which is good. Thus did <hi>Balaam</hi> here, and ſo ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers elſe-where; as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> in the behalf of <hi>Chriſt, John</hi> 11.49. And <hi>Gamaliel</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Acts</hi> 5.35. When men ſhall ſpeak but out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon illumination, ſtrength of parts, and natural ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity, or at the beſt, but out of Divine ſuggeſtion and impulſe, and the like, here <hi>Balaam</hi> is no better than his <hi>Aſs,</hi> which upon occaſion ſpeaks as well as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or like a Trunk, which nothing ſavours of the words which are conveyed through it, but in it ſelf is ſtill the ſame.</p>
            <p>This is a good Item to us eſpecially which are <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and Preachers,
<note place="margin">A Caution.</note> who by reaſon of our Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the work it ſelf which wee are exerciſed in, are caſt upon good Diſcourſes, as I may ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee are aware, not to reſt our ſelves ſatisfyed in them meerly as <hi>ſuch,</hi> but to labour to find our hearts in them, and to have ſome ſavour upon our own ſpirits of that which comes from us. It is not ſo much what <hi>wee ſay,</hi> as what <hi>wee are;</hi> nor ſo much what comes <hi>from</hi> us, as what is indeed wrought <hi>in</hi> us; when wee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part not only the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but in this ſenſe alſo our <hi>own Souls,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks. Then are Sermons,
<note place="margin">1 Theſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8</note> and Treatiſes, and good Speeches, that which they ſhould bee, when they carry upon them an impreſſion of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114972:12"/>Spirit of thoſe they come from, and that ſavoury and ſanctified with Grace. Otherwiſe they may profit others, but will little benefit thoſe themſelves whoſe they are, except it be ſo much the more to aggravate and increaſe their Condemnation, and to judge them out of their own mouthes.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly,
<note place="margin">2 An Enemy.</note> As <hi>Balaam</hi> was a wicked man, and yet ſpake that which was good; ſo an Enemy, and yet that which was comfortable. God will not only confound the Churches Adverſaries in their Plots and Conſpiracies againſt it, but will likewiſe make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be proclamers and publiſhers of it. He will make their <hi>Tongues</hi> the conveyers of comfort, where their <hi>Heads</hi> are the contrivers of miſchief. As <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>David, Thou ſhalt both do great things, and alſo ſhalt ſtill prevail,</hi> 1 Sam. 26.25. Thus we ſee this truth alſo in the Reflexion, and in reference to the party that ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered it, even wicked <hi>Balaam.</hi> This is one of his Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegms, <hi>Surely there is no inchantment againſt</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Where (before we proceed to the Second part of the Text) we may look upon <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> in one Notion and Acception more than as yet we have done,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Moral.</note> and that is by conſidering it in <hi>its Moral.</hi> And here two things more; Firſt, as an expreſſion of <hi>integrity; Jacob</hi> a plain man, as the Scripture ſtiles him; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as an expreſſion of <hi>importunity; Iſrael,</hi> a <hi>Prince with God;</hi> which gives us a double qualification in Gods people,
<note place="margin">2 Integrity.</note> intitling them to <hi>this</hi> protection. Firſt, ſo farre forth as they <hi>are upright,</hi> and ſincere, and plain-hearted; No inchantment againſt <hi>Jacob.</hi> When men are free from Plottings <hi>themſelves,</hi> they are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt to be free from the miſchief of the Plottings <hi>of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114972:12"/>other men.</hi> God takes a ſpecial delight in a ſimple-hearted Chriſtian, that hath no reaches,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.47. 2 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3. 2 Importunity.</note> nor fetches in him <hi>an Iſraelite indeed in whom is no guile,</hi> and partaking of <hi>the ſimplicity which is in Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, Thoſe which <hi>are much in acquaintance</hi> and communion with him, which are <hi>Iſraelites, Princes with God,</hi> to <hi>wraſtle and contend</hi> with him in prayer. Theſe <hi>do ſtave off</hi> many an evil which others fall into. The <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Church are above all the <hi>Anathemaes</hi> of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; what though <hi>they</hi> curſe, ſo <hi>theſe</hi> pray? what though they (as we ſee in Popery) ſend forth their <hi>Bulls,</hi> and Execrations, and Maledictions againſt the Servants of God, yet they ſhall be all of no effect, except it be like ſo many Arrows falling upon the heads of thoſe that ſhoot them up. And ſo now I have done with the firſt general Part of the Text, which is the Deliverance and Preſervation it ſelf, by way of ſolemn Declaration; <hi>Surely there is no Inchantment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Jacob, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Second is the <hi>Celebration</hi> of the Deliverance by way of Prophetical Prediction.
<note place="margin">Second, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. The celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</note> 
               <hi>According to this time,</hi> &amp;c. wherein again we have two Branches more; Firſt, the Prediction it ſelf, <hi>It ſhall be ſaid, What hath God wrought!</hi> Secondly, the <hi>particular Regulation of it,</hi> or Qualification of the performance, <hi>according to this time.</hi> For the firſt, the Prediction it ſelf; This it does ſignifie to us, what account ſhall be made of Gods Mercies and Deliverances of his Church <hi>in future A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>then</hi> be ſpoken of in the world, and that two manner of ways; Firſt, by way of <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement,</hi> and Secondly, by way of <hi>Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> by way of ſimple acknowledgement, <hi>It ſhall be ſaid,</hi> and by way of greater Aſtoniſhment, <hi>what hath God wrought!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:114972:13"/>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 By way of Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> It ſhall be <hi>ſpoken</hi> of and acknowledged; <hi>It ſhall be ſaid what God hath wrought,</hi> as ſome Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters render the words, taking <hi>them abſolutely.</hi> And ſo there is no more than this in it; That the goodneſs of God to his People, in his Deliverances and Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them, it is ſuch, as even ſucceeding Ages and Generations ſhall take notice of. Though it be done <hi>but now,</hi> yet it ſhall <hi>be ſaid</hi> and ſpoken of <hi>hereafter. This ſhall be written for the Generation to come, and the people which are not yet born ſhall praiſe the Lord,</hi> Pſalm 102.18. Therefore in ſome Tranſlations we finde it <hi>thus;</hi> It ſhal be ſaid <hi>in time</hi> what God hath wrought; In time, that is, in <hi>its due time;</hi> though <hi>now</hi> perhaps it be not ſpoken of, yet <hi>then</hi> it ſhall; or <hi>if now,</hi> yet and <hi>then</hi> too, according to that of the Prophet, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.5. <hi>O my people, remember now what</hi> Balak <hi>the King of</hi> Moab <hi>conſulted, and what</hi> Balaam <hi>the Son of</hi> Beor <hi>anſwered him from</hi> Shittim <hi>unto</hi> Gilgal, <hi>that yee may know the righteouſneſs of the Lord. Now,</hi> for ſo many years after that this Mercy and Deliverance is paſt, yet <hi>now</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it.</p>
            <p>This God will have to be ſo,
<note place="margin">1 For the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God.</note> for ſundry ends; firſt, for his own Glory, that Himſelf may have the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter renown, and his Attributes may be declared in the world; <hi>therefore</hi> it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>That his Name may be known through the earth,</hi> and <hi>that all the ends of the earth may ſee the ſalvation of our God,</hi> Pſal. 98.3. God gets himſelf Honour hereby, as he did upon <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 For the ſhame of the Enemy.</note> For the ſhame of his Enemies, and thoſe which conſpired againſt his people; it ſhall be ſaid <hi>for their reproach,</hi> and as a perpetual blot upon them to all Poſterity. And there is a double Diſgrace which comes to them by this means: Firſt, A Diſgrace from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114972:13"/>their Attempt; And ſecondly,
<note place="margin">1 In their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> A Diſgrace from their Diſ-appointment. Diſgrace from both. From their Attempt firſt, When ever it ſhall be mentioned, what they have endeavored againſt Gods people, it will lie as a reproach upon them, that it ſhould ever enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts to deviſe and contrive ſuch a wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as that was. This very <hi>thought</hi> of fooliſhneſs is ſin, and a blemiſh to the ſinner. But then again from <hi>their Diſ-appointment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment.</note> When thoſe which were ſo confident ſhall be confounded in their greateſt confidence; and notwithſtanding all their braggings and boaſtings, ſhall be able to accompliſh ſo little; what a Diſgrace will this be to them for ever, and ſtanding upon record? as ye know it was with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>the Egyptians;</hi> and it is ſaid of them to this day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.9, 10. <hi>The Enemy ſaid, I will purſue, I will over take, I will divide the ſpoil, my luſt ſhall be ſatisfied upon them, I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> Here are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of big threatning words; but whatfollows? <hi>Thou didſt blow with thy wind, the Sea covered them, they ſank as lead in the mighty waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">The comfort of the Church.</note> For the comfort alſo of <hi>the Church</hi> and people of God; It ſhall <hi>be ſaid,</hi> that ſo <hi>they</hi> may be in couraged. The remembrance of Gods goodneſs in former ages, it is a great heartning to Poſterity, and gives them occaſion to relye upon him for time to come, as we ſhall ſee more anon out of the Text.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid here <hi>indefinitely and imperſonally,
<note place="margin">It ſhal be ſaid</note> It ſhall be ſaid;</hi> but by <hi>whom</hi> it ſhall be ſaid, it is not ſaid, to ſignifie indeed,
<note place="margin">1 By the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> that it ſhall be ſaid by <hi>all ſorts</hi> of people; it ſhall be in <hi>every ones</hi> mouth. Firſt, It ſhall be ſaid by <hi>the Enemies;</hi> even <hi>they</hi> ſhall take notice of it, from the eminency, and remarkableneſs which is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114972:14"/>in it. The contrivers of the <hi>Miſchief</hi> ſhall be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamers of the <hi>deliverance,</hi> and be ſo far convinced of Gods vigilancy, and activity for his people, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it amongſt <hi>themſelves.</hi> Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.2. <hi>Then they ſaid among the</hi> HEATHEN, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for them.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.10. <hi>Be ſtill, and know that I am God; I will be exalted among the Heathen, I will be exalted in the Earth.</hi> And again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9. <hi>Their ſeed ſhall be known among the Gentiles, and their off-ſpring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people. All that ſee them ſhall acknowledge them to be the people which the Lord hath bleſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly,
<note place="margin">2 By the Church.</note> It ſhall be ſaid by <hi>the Church</hi> and their Poſterity, more eſpecially, as thoſe which are moſt eſpecially <hi>intereſted</hi> and concerned in it. Becauſe it ſhall be ſaid <hi>of Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for <hi>the occaſion;</hi> therefore, it ſhall be ſaid <hi>by Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the <hi>celebration:</hi> Therefore, in the place before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted does <hi>the Church,</hi> as it were, take it at the <hi>rebound,</hi> and <hi>eccho's</hi> to it. <hi>Then they ſaid among the Heathen, The Lord hath done great things for</hi> THEM. <hi>The Lord hath done great things for</hi> US, <hi>whereof we are glad.</hi> It is but <hi>natural</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> to ſay it, whiles the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> ſay it afore them; and accordingly, ſo they <hi>ſhall,</hi> and ſo they <hi>ought.</hi> It is <hi>our duty</hi> to be mindful, and talkative of the goodneſs of God to us in the times and generations which are paſt, <hi>This and That hath God done.</hi> As it ſhould be often in <hi>our memories,</hi> and thoughts, and meditations, and mental reflexions; ſo it ſhould be often likewiſe in <hi>our lips,</hi> and mouths, and ſpeeches, and daily converſe: we ſhould be ever and anon, as we have occaſion, ſpeaking of them. As for other matters, we can ſpeak of them frequently enough; if it be any of <hi>our own</hi> performances,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114972:14"/>any thing that <hi>we our ſelves</hi> have done, <hi>this</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſaid,</hi> and ſaid, and ſaid, and ſaid over again; we have <hi>never done</hi> talking of it, but repeat it, even to <hi>vanity it ſelf.</hi> Yea,
<note place="margin">We ſhould ſpeak of the mercies of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages.</note> but we ſhould rather be mindful to recount what <hi>God</hi> hath done for us, as a chief part of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; And yet (when we think of it) how dry and barren are we for the moſt part in this particular? How ſeldom do we practice this Duty, which wee now ſpeak of? how do the Mercies of God rather <hi>die</hi> and go out with us? were it not for ſome <hi>ſingular kind of men</hi> who have taken pains in ſuch buſineſſes as theſe are to divulge them, and tranſmit them by <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi> or were it not for ſuch <hi>ſolemn Times</hi> as theſe are, which are ſet apart on purpoſe for their <hi>Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration,</hi> they would be as things which were <hi>never done or thought of</hi> in the world. Now we ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be henceforth <hi>quickned</hi> and provoked hereunto. What? hath God <hi>done?</hi> and ſhall not we <hi>ſpeak?</hi> Hath he <hi>wrought?</hi> and ſhall not we <hi>declare?</hi> Hath he <hi>accompliſhed?</hi> and ſhall it <hi>not be ſaid?</hi> How ill does this ſilence become us, eſpecially conſidering how <hi>our ſelves</hi> are ſo much intereſted in it as we are, in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great degree?</p>
            <p>But again,
<note place="margin">We ſhould convey our own mercies to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</note> As we ſhould be ſpeaking of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God to our <hi>Progenitors,</hi> ſo we ſhould likewiſe be ſpeaking of <hi>our own Mercies</hi> and Deliverances to <hi>our children,</hi> and convey them down to poſterity, that ſtill <hi>it may be ſaid. Tell it your childrens children, and let your children tell it their children, and their children to another Generation,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaks in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 1.3. We ſhould do as much here for <hi>our Poſterity,</hi> as our Fore-fathers have done for <hi>us; Not biding it from our children, but ſhewing to the Generations
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114972:15"/>to come, the praiſes of the Lord, his ſtrength, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works that he hath done, Pſal.</hi> 78.4. Parents ſhould to this purpoſe inſtruct their Children, and Maſters of Families, thoſe which belong unto them. As they ſhould inſtruct them <hi>in other things,</hi> in the Grounds and <hi>Principles of Religion,</hi> and the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtianity,</hi> and the way to eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; So alſo moreover, upon occaſion, in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Providence,</hi> and the Diſpenſations of God to his Church, in the deliverance of it: They ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate them and unfold them, ſo far forth as they are capable of them, in all the particular Branches, and Circumſtances, and Appurtenances of them, whereby they may diſtinctly underſtand them. This was that which the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Gods people, were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of, and accordingly, God expected it from them, as you may ſee touching <hi>the Paſſover,</hi> Exod. 12.26, 27. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, when your children-ſhall ſay unto you, What mean you by this ſervice? that ye ſhall ſay, It is the ſacrifice of the Lords Paſſover, who paſſed over the houſes of the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in</hi> Egypt, <hi>when he ſmote the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>and delivered our houſes.</hi> And ſo of the <hi>ſtones</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> Joſh. 4.21. <hi>When your children ſhall ask their Fathers in time to come, ſaying, What mean theſe ſtones? Then ſhall you let your children know, ſaying;</hi> Iſrael <hi>came over this</hi> Jordan <hi>on dry land, for the Lord your God dried up the waters of</hi> Jordan <hi>before you.</hi> Thus I ſay are Parents to teach and inform their children in ſuch like paſſages, that it <hi>may be ſaid what God hath wrought.</hi> And thus much for the word of <hi>acknowledgement,</hi> or Commemoration.</p>
            <p>The next is the word <hi>of Aſtoniſhment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> or Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by carrying it a little higher, and with ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114972:15"/>further elevation; which is a great deal more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Text, and more emphatical. WHAT HATH GOD WROUGHT! that is, what a ſtrange and unheard of deliverance hath the Lord brought about for his people! This is that which the Scripture does abundantly teſtifie to us, the wonderfulneſs and miraculouſneſs of Gods proceedings in this regard. Indeed (if we ſpeak at large) <hi>all</hi> the works of God, they are in their kind works <hi>of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> There is nothing which he does or ever did, but it hath matter of <hi>wonderment</hi> in it.
<note place="margin">Iſay 6, 9.</note> As his <hi>Name</hi> is WONDERFUL, ſo are his <hi>Works.</hi> Look upon his works of <hi>Creation,</hi> and we may very well ſay of <hi>them,</hi> what hath God wrought! As <hi>David</hi> himſelf does, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.3. <hi>When I conſider the Heavens, the work of thy ſingers, &amp;c. O Lord, our Lord, how excellent is thy Name, &amp;c.</hi> And when he ſpeaks but of his <hi>own framing,</hi> I am <hi>fearfully and wonderfully made.</hi> And <hi>marvelous are thy works, and that my Soul knoweth right well, Pſal.</hi> 139.14. Take him further in his <hi>Works of Redemption,</hi> and the new Creature, And what hath God wrought there? in changing our Natures, in ſtamping his own Image upon us, in conforming us to himſelf, in tranſlating us from darkneſs to light, from death to life, from the power of Satan, to God: What a <hi>wonderful</hi> work is this to all thoſe, who are made ſenſible and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of it! Oh <hi>The depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God!</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. But yet none of theſe are meant here in this Text.
<note place="margin">The Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Church won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully.</note> We are in this place to underſtand it concerning the works of <hi>his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> in the deliverance of his Church; God is here oftentimes very admirable, and full of wonder, and we may very well ſay of them indeed, <hi>What hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114972:16"/>God wrought?</hi> The Scripture is full of expreſſions to this purpoſe; Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.11, 12. It is ſaid of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, That they forgate his works, and his wonders that he had ſhown them. Marvelous things that he did in the ſight of their Fathers.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.5. <hi>Remember the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous works that he hath done.</hi> And ſo in other places he is ſaid to be <hi>wonderful in working and doing wonders, Exod.</hi> 15.11. As he is ſo in many things elſe, ſo more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in his delivering of his Church. The paſſages of Gods Providence here are wonderful, in ſundry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1 From its Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability.</note> In regard of the <hi>Unlikelihood and improbability</hi> of the things themſelves. They are wonderful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>unexpected:</hi> That which a man did not look for, when he beholds it, he wonders at it. The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of things improbable and unlikely they cauſe aſtoniſhment. Why, thus are the dealings of God with his Church many times, in this reſpect. He delivers them where they do not expect it, nor can ſee any likelihood for it; yea, rather, where they ſee every thing oppoſite and contrary hereunto. And ſo the <hi>Arabick</hi> tranſlation (though not in our laſt Printed Copy) yet according to the <hi>Erpenian</hi> Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeems to carry it in the very Text. <hi>God hath wrought a</hi> DESPERATE <hi>thing.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Companions in their great danger in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> ſays, <hi>They were preſt out of meaſure, above ſtrength, inſomuch, that they deſpaired even of life, and had the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death in themſelves, and yet God delivered them from ſo great a death.</hi> It was ſo in the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1. <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity of</hi> Sion, <hi>we were like to them that dream:</hi> Why like them that <hi>dream?</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114972:16"/>in regard of the ſtrangeneſs, it was ſuch as they could not think there was any truth or reality in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as to the manner of Tranſaction,
<note place="margin">2 The manner of tranſaction.</note> theſe Providences are wonderful <hi>ſo,</hi> and we may be very well amazed at them upon that account. <hi>What hath God wrought,</hi> as to the <hi>means</hi> which he hath wrought <hi>it by;</hi> ſuch poor and contemptible inſtruments as he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now and then to imploy, and to make uſe of for the deliverance of his people!</p>
            <p>And then thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 The unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of the Perſons.</note> The unworthineſs of the perſons which are made partakers of it, this advances it ſo much the more; for God to work ſo ſtrongly and powerfully for thoſe which deſerve ſo little at his hands, as he ſometimes does; this is a Wonder of Wonders, and which may very well work us to <hi>Aſtoniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this comes to this purpoſe,
<note place="margin">1 Admire Gods Providence to his Church.</note> That we for our parts be ſo much the more affected with his dealings with us, we ſhould not look upon them as ordinary matters, but as things above common performance, and ſo they are. As the things themſelves are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſo accordingly ſhould they be admired by us, and we ſhould bleſs and praiſe him for them upon his conſideration, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> teaches us to do, chap. 25. ver. 1. <hi>O Lord, thou art my God, I will exalt thee, I will praiſe thy Name, for thou haſt done wonderful things, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, it ſhould teach us to truſt in God,
<note place="margin">2 Truſt him in difficulties.</note> and to depend upon him in caſes of <hi>difficulty.</hi> Wee ſhould not deſpair in the greateſt Extremities, nor <hi>limit the Holy one of Iſrael;</hi> for God, he <hi>works Wonders</hi> for his people, and ſuch as they themſelves are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pre-conceive, or to imagine <hi>how</hi> they ſhould be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114972:17"/>wrought. It is a great piece of weakneſs in us, when we ſhall meaſure the Power of God by our poor and ſhallow apprehenſions. That becauſe we forſooth cannot ſee how ſuch and ſuch things ſhould be done <hi>in our reaſon,</hi> therefore they cannot be done at all. O let us take heed of that, God does ſometimes bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſuch things for his Church and People, as they themſelves ſhall be ready to <hi>Wonder</hi> at then when they are done. And ſo much of the firſt Branch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in this ſecond General, viz. The Prediction, or Celebration it ſelf, <hi>It ſhall be ſaid of Jacob, and of Iſrael, what hath God wrought!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Qualification,
<note place="margin">The regulation of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</note> or particular <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation</hi> of it, <hi>according to this time.</hi> Now this again it may be underſtood two manner of ways, either as the <hi>Occaſion,</hi> or as the <hi>Pattern.</hi> According to this time, that is, <hi>derivatively</hi> from it; or according to this time, that is,
<note place="margin">1 As the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</note> 
               <hi>proportionably</hi> to it. Anſwerable to Gods Goodneſs <hi>in this Mercy,</hi> ſhall be his Goodneſs in many <hi>others.</hi> Firſt, take it as the occaſion; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this time, that is, with reſpect had unto it; when future Ages ſhall reflect upon the Mercy which God hath vouchſafed to his people, in their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from this Conſpiracy, they ſhall exceedingly bleſs him for it, and ſay, <hi>What hath he done?</hi> they ſhall not only take notice of <hi>the Deliverance,</hi> as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the <hi>Church,</hi> but of the <hi>Author</hi> of it, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <hi>God himſelf;</hi> not only ſay, <hi>what is wrought,</hi> as to the <hi>meer event,</hi> but what hath <hi>God</hi> wrought, as point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the <hi>Worker</hi> of it. There were divers occaſions of Thankfulneſs and Acknowledgement in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as fit to be celebrated by them. Firſt, The diſappointment of <hi>Balak</hi> in his intendments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114972:17"/>them. Secondly, Not only diſappointing him of his intended Curſe, but alſo vouchſafing a Bleſſing inſtead of it; this was ſomewhat more. Then third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That all this ſhould be done ſo publickly, and with ſo much ſolemnity, as it appeared to be from the circumſtances; As it was matter of <hi>Aſtoniſhment,</hi> ſo it was likewiſe matter of <hi>Acknowledgement;</hi> as of <hi>Admiration,</hi> ſo alſo of <hi>Thankfulneſs.</hi> And according to this time, that is, for the Mercy that was <hi>wrought</hi> at this time, it ſhall bee ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael, What hath God wrought.</hi> That as the Occaſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We may take it alſo <hi>as the Pattern,
<note place="margin">2 As the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern.</note> according to this time, &amp;c.</hi> that is, look how God hath done at preſent, the like will he do alſo hereafter. Theſe words, <hi>It ſhall be ſaid,</hi> do not only denote the <hi>acknowledgement</hi> and celebration, in regard of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> but alſo the <hi>ground</hi> of it, in regard of the thing, there ſhall <hi>be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> for <hi>this ſaying</hi> afforded to <hi>following times,</hi> agreeable to what there is <hi>now.</hi> There are two Concluſions which do hence natually ariſe from theſe words; Firſt, That God will be one and the ſame to his Church in all Ages and Generations of the World, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and preſervation of them. Secondly, That there are now and then ſome ſtanding and more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Deliverances which God vouchſafes to his Church and People, and which he propounds alſo to himſelf, as ſo many patterns and examples of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, God is the ſame to his Church in all Ages; as he hath been in former times, ſo he will likewiſe be in this, and ſo downward, even to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt. God is as careful of his Church now, as ever he was, and Chriſt hath as great a regard to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114972:18"/>his Spouſe now, as ever he had; be loves her never a whit the leſs becauſe of her age; nay rather, if there be any difference at all, he loves her ſo much the more, ſhee is ſo much the dearer with him, as ſhee hath longerhad relation to him.</p>
            <p>This point which we are now upon,
<note place="margin">2 From Gods unchangeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> is grounded upon theſe conſiderations; Firſt, the Unchangeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is in God himſelf conſidered in his own Nature; <hi>I the Lord</hi> change not, therefore yee Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> are not conſumed, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. God is the ſame <hi>in himſelf,</hi> therefore the ſame alſo in his dealings, and paſſages of Providence towards his <hi>Church.</hi> He <hi>does</hi> the ſame, becauſe <hi>he is</hi> the ſame; <hi>Thou art the ſame,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.27. As the ſame for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of <hi>being,</hi> ſo the ſame for the continuance of <hi>properties,</hi> and attributes conſiderable in themſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2 Unchanged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Enemy.</note> There is the unchangeableneſs, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changedneſs rather of <hi>the enemies, they</hi> are the ſame for their affection and behaviour. If <hi>the enemies</hi> of the Church were leſſe wicked and malicious than ever they had been, the <hi>Preſerver</hi> of the Church needed not to be ſo vigilent and watchful over it; God might abate of his care, if men did abate of their malice; but now there is the ſame naughtineſs and cruelty in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>men,</hi> and therefore the ſame activity <hi>in God. Balaam</hi> was not only confined to the times of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he lives even <hi>ſtill, now,</hi> and to this day we have thoſe which are true and perfect reſemblances of him, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> hath fore told it long ago, ſpeaking of the latter times, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray, following the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>the Son of</hi> Baſor, <hi>who loved the wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, &amp;c. Satan,</hi> he is as buſie himſelf, and as mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114972:18"/>as ever he was, and his <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> they are acted by the ſame curſed Principles as before; there is no change nor amendment of them at all, but one Generation and age, and it is a lively Picture and Image of the other. Look what <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi> were in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, the ſame were the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time; and what the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, the ſame are divers others in <hi>ours;</hi> nothing better, if not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worſe. That enmity which was fore-told ſhould be put between the ſeed of the Serpent, and the ſeed of the Woman, it holds out to this preſent day, from the beginning of the World, without any diminution at all. Juſt as it is alſo with other fierce and cruel Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the ſame nature with them, Wolves, and Tigres, and Bears, and Leopards; they have ſtill the ſame diſpoſitions that they ever had from the fall of man; ſo alſo have theſe enemies, and perſecutors, that are ſo like unto them, which lays a ſecond ground for this equal carriage of God towards his Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">3 The unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedueſſe of the Church.</note> Gods people themſelves are carried by the ſame Principles likewiſe that ever they have been; There is the ſame gracious Spirit in them, which hath been in times paſt; The ſame Spirit of Prayer, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and Supplications, and they are as able to prevail with God as ever they were. As there have been heretofore <hi>Moſeſes,</hi> and <hi>Jaeobs,</hi> and <hi>Daniels,</hi> and <hi>Jobs,</hi> and the like; ſo there are ſtill the ſame <hi>now. The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man,</hi> it is able to do as much <hi>now,</hi> as ever it was, as the Apoſtle ſeems to intimate, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Prayer,</hi> it hath not loſt one jot of its primitive efficacy, nor <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of Prayer. A true child of God indeed which is in Covenant &amp; favour with him, and actual terms of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114972:19"/>Peace and Reconciliation, he may as boldly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently go to him in the behalf of his Church <hi>now,</hi> as ever could <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Elias</hi> himſelf <hi>heretofore,</hi> and may be as ſure to ſpeed and to prevail in theſe his Addreſles, as ever they might; having the ſame <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and the ſame <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> and Interceſſor, and Mediator, as any of them had, and this latter, with greater advantage. As there is no decay in the <hi>World</hi> (which ſome have taken pains to prove) ſo neither in the <hi>Church;</hi> Which therefore may expect the ſame dealings from God himſelf, in the ſame circumſtances, that ever he hath ſhown.</p>
            <p>And further as for the <hi>whole Church</hi> at large,
<note place="margin">An incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cceſſion.</note> ſo for thoſe which are <hi>ſpecial parts,</hi> and members of it, it is an incouragement to <hi>them</hi> likewiſe: To <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that Chriſt would not be onely with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but with <hi>ſucceeding Teachers; Loe I am with you alway, even to the end of the World, Matth.</hi> 28.20. And ſo for <hi>Magiſtrates;</hi> not onely with <hi>Moſes,</hi> but with <hi>Joſhua, As I have been with</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo will I be with thee, Joſh.</hi> 1.5. God does not onely continue the <hi>Place</hi> and office, but he continues the <hi>aſsiſtance,</hi> becauſe the <hi>work</hi> is the ſame, therefore will he afford the ſame ſtrength for the diſcharge of it. God is the ſame to his Church and people in one age of the World as in another. That is the firſt Propoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is not unlike to it, and that is this; That God is pleaſed to make ſome Deliverances to be as it were <hi>ſtandards</hi> and patterns to the reſt. This Mercy of God to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in delivering them from the Curſing of <hi>Balaam,</hi> upon the importunity of <hi>Balak,</hi> it ſhould be a <hi>copy</hi> which God would ſet to himſelf in his following Deliverings of them. He would deal with them all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114972:19"/>along much alike as he had done <hi>in this.</hi> All Gods carriages to his people, they are the Diſpenſations of much loving kindneſs, but there are ſome which are more eminent than others; and from whence they may in ſpecial conclude of his care and watchfulneſs over them; ſuch was this in this particular Scripture. And therefore when God would perſwade his people of his favour and good will towards them, he calls them to the remembrance of <hi>this</hi> in the place before alledged; <hi>O my people, remember now what</hi> Balak <hi>the King of</hi> Moab <hi>conſulted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.5. why re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that? becauſe it was a more eminent Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and a pledge of many more anſwerable to it. So their Deliverance out of the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> out of the Houſe of Bondage; it was a Deliverance of the ſame nature with it, and ſuch as God makes mention of to them, when he gives them his Law upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> as that which might ſtick cloſer by them, <hi>I am the Lord thy God that brought thee up out of the Land of Aegypt,</hi> Exod. 20.2. ſo afterwards when they were delivered out of <hi>Captivity,</hi> and reſtored to their own Land again; <hi>this</hi> it was a remarkable Deliverance, and ſuch as was made, as it were, to ſwallow up the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As we may ſee in <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.7, 8. <hi>Therefore behold the days come (ſaith the Lord) that they ſhall no more ſay, The Lord liveth, which brought up the Children of Iſrael out of the Land of</hi> Aegypt. <hi>But the Lord liveth which brought up, and which led the Seed of the Houſe of Iſrael out of the North-Country, and from all Countries whither I had driven them.</hi> Their <hi>return from Captivity,</hi> it was more ſtrange than <hi>their deliverance from</hi> Aegypt, and ſuch which ſhould be more frequently in their mouthes, as the great Mercy, and Deliverance of all.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114972:20"/>
            <p>This God does chiefly ſo order for the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our weak faith,
<note place="margin">For the ſtrengthening of Faith.</note> that ſo we might have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to hold to, and to fly back to, and to recover our ſelves by, even then when we have, as it <hi>were, loſt</hi> our ſelves, as concerning the apprehenſions of his love. Ordinary and common favours, though they are good teſtimonies of Gods Affection to his people, his daily preſervation of us, and his continual watching over us for good, and his conſtant providing for us, yet theſe for the moſt part do very eaſily ſlip out of our mindes, and paſs us without any great obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, But now theſe <hi>Great ones,</hi> they will a little ſtick by us, for ſo much better confirmation of our faith, and we may make exceeding great uſe of them in temptation and time of need. Thus is one greater <hi>Temporal</hi> Mercy a pledge and aſſurance of a <hi>leſs.</hi> And thus again is a <hi>Spiritual deliverance,</hi> a pledge, and an aſſurance of a <hi>Temporal.</hi> And Faith it will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly improve it, and draw it forth, as occaſion ſhall ſerve. There is a double end in the Deliverances which God at any time gives us, not only as they are comfortable in themſelves, but likewiſe as they are fore-runners of more, and have others in the bowels of them.</p>
            <p>This ſhould teach us therefore to improve ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages as theſe are for our greater comfort,
<note place="margin">Improvement.</note> both in our own particular caſes, as alſo in the caſe of the Church; for our ſelves, if we be in any ſtrait or difficulty, or perplexity whatſoever;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> For our ſelves.</note> there are <hi>Times</hi> which wee may call to minde, and according to which we may reckon of Gods goodneſs to us; when we were once in ſuch a danger and God delivered us from it; lay under ſuch a Sickneſs, and were recovered of <hi>that;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114972:20"/>were brought into ſuch an Exigence, and God found out a way for our relief. According to <hi>this time</hi> it ſhall be ſaid <hi>of</hi> us, and <hi>by</hi> us, <hi>What hath God wrought!</hi> It is a great fault and infirmity in us that we do no more make uſe of Experiences in this kinde, than we do, for the incouragement of our ſelves. We ſhould keep a Regiſter of Gods favours to this purpoſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Greater</hi> favours, and which are <hi>Patterns</hi> of Gods goodneſs to us; We may have as much comfort from an <hi>Experience</hi> now and then as we may from a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and it may be (as it may ſo fall out) a great deal more, as being accommodated to our outward ſenſe; but eſpecially <hi>upon</hi> a promiſe, and <hi>ſeconding</hi> it, will it be effectual to us.</p>
            <p>Again ſecondly, As in our <hi>own particular,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 For the Church.</note> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the Church of God in general, we ſhould improve our Experiences here alſo. It was that which God laid to the charge of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they <hi>forgat his Works, and</hi> the <hi>Wonders</hi> which he had ſhewen amongſt them, forgat them? How ſo? What is the meaning of that? Not that they were abſolutely out of their memories, <hi>that</hi> they could not well be, but they forgat them ſo as to <hi>apply</hi> them, and to make <hi>uſe</hi> of them now upon occaſion; ſo they forgat them; they forgat them ſo as to be <hi>thankful,</hi> and they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat them ſo as to be <hi>fruitful,</hi> and they forgat them ſo as to be <hi>faithful;</hi> They were to them in regard of any <hi>Benefit</hi> or Spiritual good which they got by them, as things which had been never done amongſt them. This was that which the Lord did ſo deeply cenſure in them, in that they queſtioned, Whether he who had done ſo much for them already, were able to do as much again. This it was very <hi>vile</hi> and unworthy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114972:21"/>in them; No, but they ſhould have rather upon ſuch and ſuch an Experience have reaſoned as here in the Text; According to this time, &amp;c. So much of <hi>that</hi> Branch, viz. The regulation of the performance; and ſo much alſo of the <hi>whole Text,</hi> as it lyes before us here in this Scripture.</p>
            <p>ANd now to bring the <hi>Text</hi> and the <hi>Occaſion</hi> both together;
<note place="margin">The Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text to the Occaſion.</note> this day is this Scripture ſulfilled in your ears; and not in <hi>your ears</hi> only, but in <hi>your eyes;</hi> we all both to the glory of God, and our own peace and comfort ſee this truth verified to us, <hi>That there is no Inchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>nor any Divination againſt Iſrael.</hi> We cannot ſay there hath been none in regard of <hi>Attempt,</hi> no more than <hi>Jacob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> could ſay in regard of <hi>then ſelves,</hi> for <hi>that</hi> there hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently and apparently enough. There hath not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the working of Inchantments, nor Divinations neither; we have had both the <hi>Conſultations</hi> of <hi>Balak,</hi> and the Anſwers alſo of <hi>Balaam</hi> againſt us. This <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plot</hi> wherein the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Body of this. Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was by the Deviſers of it devoted to deſtruction, what was it elſe but an <hi>Inchantment againſt</hi> our Jacob and Iſrael? <hi>Inchantment</hi> we know whence it is fetcht, it is a word which ſmels of the Vault, which ſavours of <hi>Hell,</hi> and takes in the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf for the efficacy of it. And certainly if Hell at any time were in any thing ſet on work here upon earth, it was undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Conſpiracy. It was the Devils <hi>Maſter-peece,</hi> and ſuch, as it is a great Queſtion (ſeeing that this hath failed) whether he hath ever ſuch another or no; ſure we are if there bee ſuch another it muſt come from <hi>Him,</hi> for the Monſtrouſneſs and Prodigiouſneſs of it.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:114972:21"/>
            <p>Where (becauſe we are now upon the <hi>Parallel</hi>) yee ſhall ſee that it was not only agreeable, but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent to that of <hi>Balaks</hi> and <hi>Balaams</hi> by farre, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Circumſtances. Firſt, if we conſider the quality and condition of the <hi>Perſons</hi> on either ſide; this will make it very different. For there in <hi>Balak</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> it was one Nation plotting againſt another; <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Midian</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Here in <hi>this</hi> of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> againſt their <hi>own Country-men,</hi> Kindred, Bloud, Alliance. Now, in all miſchievous attempts, <hi>Unnaturalneſs</hi> is ever an aggravation; where Nature is moſt extinguiſht (which in ſome things is a great reſtraint) wickedneſs is there moſt notorious, and ſo it was here. Then ſecondly conſider the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Provocation;</hi> In the doing of another an ill turn (though it doth not excuſe to be provoked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhould be ſo much meekneſs as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe injuries which are offered) yet where the Provocation is the leſs, the Iniquity is the greater. To harm thoſe that do not hurt us, nor we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any wrong from them, nor cauſe to fear it, it is ſo much the more abominable. And this was the caſe again here, above that of <hi>Moab</hi> to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for <hi>there</hi> there was ſome cauſe of <hi>jealouſie,</hi> and probable danger from them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.4. <hi>Moab</hi> ſaid to the Elders of <hi>Midian, Now ſhall this company lick up all that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, as the Oxe licketh up the Graſs of the Field.</hi> There was no ſuch matter in <hi>this;</hi> they were Perſons which were <hi>tolerated,</hi> connived at, favoured, had received many courteſies from the State in which they were, and <hi>yet</hi> could finde in their hearts thus to work againſt it. This makes it more Prodigious ſtill, and this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment more Deviliſh by farre than that in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114972:22"/>Text. Then thirdly (which is the main of all) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>matter</hi> of it likewiſe, and the thing it ſelf, which the Plot did extend to. There in <hi>Balak</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> it was only to let fall a <hi>few ill words</hi> upon them, and there was an <hi>end;</hi> to <hi>Curſe</hi> them, but ſtrike not a <hi>Aroke</hi> unleſs they began firſt. But here in this preſent deſign there was not only <hi>ſaying,</hi> but <hi>doing;</hi> not only <hi>wiſhing,</hi> but <hi>working;</hi> not only <hi>curſing,</hi> but <hi>acting;</hi> There was <hi>digging,</hi> and undermining, and barrelling and laying Trains of Powder, and more intended if God had not prevented it, and come between; it was abſolutely and directly to deſtroy without Mercy, or Pity, or Compaſſion, or Commiſeration, on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, in a moment, all at once, without any warning, King and Peers, and Judges, and Knights, and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and Burgeſſes, and a great many more beſides, Spectators and Auditors with them, the very prime and flower of the Land. A thing almoſt <hi>incredible</hi> that it ſhould come into mens <hi>Heads</hi> to <hi>think</hi> of it, into their <hi>Hearts</hi> to <hi>cloſe</hi> with it, into their <hi>Hands</hi> to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake</hi> it! Yet thus it <hi>was,</hi> we <hi>know</hi> it to be ſo, and ſhould have known it in <hi>another manner</hi> than now wee do, if that they might have had their wills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo that there is no queſtion to be made of <hi>that,</hi> but there was <hi>Inchantment</hi> enough againſt our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as to matter of <hi>Attempt; that</hi> muſt be needs acknowledged.</p>
            <p>But yet was there ſo in <hi>good earneſt?</hi> Was it indeed? Was it ſo in the <hi>effect</hi> and accompliſhment? No, <hi>that</hi> it was not, and this is that which we are now come to acknowledge this preſent day; that through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our gracious God that watched over us, <hi>There was no Inchantment againſt</hi> Jacob, <hi>nor any Divination againſt</hi> Iſrael. Our ſtate ſecured, our Religion kept
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114972:22"/>inviolate, our lives preſerved;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 124.7.</note> 
               <hi>Our ſouls eſcaped as a Bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler, the ſnare is broken and we are delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet that is not all neither; For the making of this Mercy compleat, as it was here in the caſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we are from hence not only never the <hi>worſe,</hi> but much the <hi>better;</hi> it hath tended to our greater Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and the confirmation of Gods goodneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us ever ſince. <hi>Popery</hi> hath from hence the more ſuffered (and ever ſhall) and the true Religion gained by this Conſpiracy. And this for the firſt part of the Text, brought down to the occaſion in <hi>the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now Secondly, as to the <hi>Celebration</hi> of it, we may very well adde alſo here. <hi>According to this time it ſhall be ſaid of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what hath God wrought!</hi> It ſhall be ſaid by way of <hi>Aſtoniſhment,</hi> and by way of <hi>Acknowledgement</hi> both; it ſhall be <hi>wondred</hi> at, and it ſhall <hi>be ſpoken of</hi> to all ſucceeding Ages and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; this <hi>Mercy</hi> which we this day celebrate.</p>
            <p>Firſt; I ſay it is matter of <hi>Aſtoniſhment;</hi> we may here hold up our hands and cry, <hi>VVhat hath God wrought!</hi> As we may wonder at the <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> ſo we may as well wonder at the <hi>Deliverance,</hi> eſpecially in the Circumſtances of it, and the Qualifications which it is cloathed withall; That God ſhould deliver <hi>us</hi> and <hi>us</hi> in ſuch a <hi>manner,</hi> and ſuch a way, and by ſuch means as he did, in that extremity, when the buſineſs was come ſo near to accompliſhment, as indeed it was, what a miraculous thing was this!</p>
            <p>But yet it was not ſo wonderful as that, therefore it ſhould ſtop our mouthes, and hinder our ſpeech, as matters of Wonder ſometimes do ſo amaze as that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114972:23"/>they put to <hi>ſilence;</hi> No, it ſhall be <hi>ſpoken of</hi> for all that, <hi>It ſhall be ſaid of Jacob;</hi> Said? <hi>when</hi> ſhould it be ſo? It may be juſt at that time when the thing was <hi>newly done;</hi> when <hi>Balaams</hi> mouth was wreathed to the bleſſing of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was delivered from <hi>Balak,</hi> it ſhould be ſaid <hi>then;</hi> nay not only ſo, but for a great while after, in following times. And ſo likewiſe ſhall this be of ours, it was wrought <hi>nine and forty years ago,</hi> but it ſhall be ſpoken of <hi>now,</hi> yea and nine hundred and forty years hence, and longer, if the World ſo continue; It is a <hi>Deliverance</hi> and Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is never to be forgotten by us, nor our Poſterity after us, ſo long as the Sun and Moon ſhall indure in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Yea, but it may be this was <hi>All</hi> that God ever meant to do for us, when he had delivered us from the Gunpower-Treaſon, he had then ſhewn his skil, and he could never do the like again; when he had once delivered us now, he would never deliver us <hi>more;</hi> never own us, nor look upon us as his people. It is true, we <hi>deſerved</hi> no more from him, but that this ſhould have been the very <hi>laſt</hi> Mercy and Favour that he would beſtow upon us; but yet it was not ſo, God hath more Bleſſings than one, and more for <hi>us,</hi> if wee be capable of them; his Goodneſs is from Generation to Generation. <hi>According to this time it ſhall be ſaid, what hath God wrought!</hi> Not only occaſionally <hi>from</hi> it, but proportionably <hi>to</hi> it. God hath taken <hi>Pattern,</hi> he hath taken Pattern by this ſtanding Mercy, to ſhew us Mercy in many particulars ever ſince. There are two great ſtanding Mercies, which are the pillars of Gods goodneſs to us; The one is our Deliverance from the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion</hi> in Eighty eight, and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114972:23"/>other, our Deliverance from this <hi>Powder-plot</hi> in Sixty five, and God hath perfectly kept to his Copy ever ſince.</p>
            <p>Yea and is ready to do ſo ſtill, if we be careful for our parts to be (as I ſaid) Subjects capable of it: which it concerns us to be, by a thankful improvement of thoſe Mercies which we have already received, and converſations ſuitable thereunto; Eſpecially we of this <hi>City,</hi> who have the greateſt ſhare in the Mercies of this Nation, of any other which are parts of it. Not only this particular Deliverance which now we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate, but many other Bleſſings beſides, in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency to it. When we ſhall look back upon the times lately paſt, and conſider other places of the Land, ſo terrified and diſturbed, and waſted with the late Civil Warres, whiles we our ſelves have in the mean time ſate in peace and quiet, in a manner all the while, under our own Vines, and our own Fig-trees; no ſeditions nor combuſtions amongſt us, no breaking in, nor going out, nor complaining in our ſtreets; but as the Children in the fiery Furnace, ſafe our ſelves, whiles all others conſumed about us. How well may it be here ſaid both <hi>of</hi> us, and <hi>by</hi> us, according to this time thus paſt, <hi>What hath God wrought!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as one Queſtion commonly begets another, ſo likewiſe here, This of what hath <hi>God</hi> wrought? infers this, of what <hi>have we</hi> wrought? what have <hi>we</hi> done for our particulars in anſwer to all this Goodneſs and Mercy of God towards us? It is a queſtion which will one day be asked us by one who will have Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to do it; let us afore hand ask it our ſelves, that ſo we may be able to anſwer it more comfortably <hi>then,</hi> That as God hath wrought for <hi>us,</hi> ſo <hi>we</hi> have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114972:24"/>wrought for <hi>him;</hi> and as he hath preſerved <hi>us,</hi> our Lives and Friends, and Eſtates, and all we have; ſo <hi>we</hi> have alſo (as much as we can) preſerved <hi>Him,</hi> his Truth, and Goſpel, and Government, and Glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
            <p>Beloved, we can be no further ſure of <hi>preſervation</hi> than we are careful of <hi>Innocency,</hi> when we ſhall once depart from <hi>this,</hi> we ſtrike at the very root and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all the comforts which we ever yet injoy'd, or do injoy; we forfeit our claime and title to all Gods Bleſſings of us, which we can expect upon no other terms than this of our <hi>Good behaviour,</hi> and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of our Duties in the opportunities we are intruſted withall.</p>
            <p>As for the Times in which we live, there is a great deal of uncertainty upon them, and we know not how they may prove. It will be our wiſdom therefore to get an intereſt in God, and his favour in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is better than <hi>life</hi> it ſelf, that ſo whatever befalls the <hi>VVorld,</hi> it may be ſure to be well with <hi>us</hi> for our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; <hi>Though the earth be removed, and though the mountains be carried into the midſt of the Sea,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.2.</p>
            <p>And to incourage us ſo much the more in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Gods goodneſs to us, upon our cloſing with him; let us ſtill ſet the Deliverance of <hi>this Day</hi> before our eyes, and let it be always freſh in our thoughts. Ancient and long-paſt Mercies, they are apt to be out of date with us, and loſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for their Antiquity; but that is a great peece of fondneſs and fooliſhneſs in us, whiles the things in their own nature are ſtill the ſame.</p>
            <p>As for this of our Preſervation from the <hi>Powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot;</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:114972:24"/>it will advance our thankfulneſs for it, if wee ſhall but conſider, what a miſerable condition it would have probably involved us in, if it had taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; which that we might in ſome manner gueſſe at, and conceive with our ſelves, God hath been pleaſed of late to give us ſome experiments of the force of ſuch mixtures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f. Tower-ſtreet</hi>
               </note> both in a Town in our <hi>Neighbour-Country,</hi> as alſo but a few years ſince by a ſad event here in this <hi>City;</hi> that ſo this Deliverance from <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder</hi> might the better take with us.</p>
            <p>To conclude all, Let our Experience of Gods Power and Goodneſs both, in this remarkable paſſage of his Providence ſo much the more ingage us to him, in dependance and new obedience. And for our <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> let us ſay of them as <hi>Jethro</hi> ſometime of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> the Adverſaries of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 18.11. with which I will end. <hi>Now I know that the Lord is greater than all gods, for in the thing wherein they dealt proudly he was above them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
